All right, it's time to go over
everything you need to know about a push
unit 3. And look, I'm not going to
sugarcoat it. This is the Wendy's T-Rex
equivalent of units thus far. And by the
end, if you don't feel like you've
dislocated your jaw to fit this thing in
your mouth hole, then you're doing it
wrong. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, as is my custom, let me start by
giving you the big idea that will act as
the connective tissue holding this beast
of a unit together. The time period is
1754 to 1800, which corresponds to the
beginning of the French and Indian War
and ends with the election of Thomas
Jefferson. And basically the whole
narrative here has three acts. The first
act is the causes of the American
Revolution. The second act is called a
new republic. And the third act is
migration and conflict. Okay, so that's
where we're going and that's enough
mouth hole flapping by way of prelude.
So let's jump into the first act. Okay,
now if the climax of this unit is the
American Revolution, then the inciting
incident for sure is the French and
Indian War. So basically this was a
conflict between France and Great
Britain over disputed territory here in
the Ohio River Valley. And as it turned
out, British colonists in North America
were rapidly uh multiplying, and that
meant that they very much wanted to
migrate west into the Ohio country to
find better accommodation. But as it
further turns out, the French claimed
that territory, and they were ready to
give the migrants a good French slap if
they started squatting on their land.
And to even further complicate the
matter, several indigenous groups also
lived there, and they were none too
pleased to see those wy British folk
moving in. Therefore, several American
Indian groups led by the Shaunies and
the Delawarees allied together in order
to defend their rights to this
territory. So when the British colonists
considered all of that, it put them in a
proper huff because as you might know,
the heart wants what it wants. And what
their heart wanted was the dang Ohio
country. Now, I'm not going to go into
all the details of the war except to say
this. The conflict erupted in 1754
because of a military blunder by our boy
George Washington. Although it started
on the North American continent, the war
soon spread to Europe and parts of India
and Africa as well. And that's when the
conflict became known as the Seven Years
War, which arguably was the first proper
World War. So, here's where I tell you
that Great Britain won the war to the
great annoyance of the French who
retired to their secret base, twisted
their mustache, and plotted their
revenge, and they will get that revenge,
baby. But not yet. Just put that juicy
bit in your pocket, and we'll get back
to it. But for our purposes, what you
really need to focus on is the effects
of this war. So, you know, let's talk
about it. But before I do, let me just
mention that if this video is helping
you and you want even more help getting
an A in your class and a five on your
exam in May, you might want to check out
my A Push Heimler review guide. It's got
everything you need to study as fast as
possible, including exclusive videos
that are not here on YouTube, practice
questions, practice exams, and all the
rest. So, if that's something you're
into, that link is in the description
below. Okay, so effect number one, the
Treaty of Paris, signed in 1763 changed
the map of British North America. First
of all, Spain seated Florida to Great
Britain. Wait a minute, why in the fresh
heck is Spain involved in this all of a
sudden? Well, to keep things simple, I
didn't mention before that later in the
war, Spain allied with France, so they
also had to make some concessions to
Great Britain in the peace treaty. Okay.
Second, France gave up their territory
west of the Mississippi River to Spain.
And then third, and most important,
France seated their territory in the
Ohio River Valley to Great Britain. And
hey, that's everything the colonist ever
dreamed of, right? Like westward
migration level 10 commence. But hold on
right there, because the second effect
of the war was that Great Britain went
ahead and prevented westward expansion
for its colonists. And they did this by
drawing the proclamation line of 1763,
which forbade British colonists from
migrating west beyond the Appalachian
Mountains. And the reason Big Mama
Britain laid down this law is because
winning this war cost her a fortune. And
that meant she had no additional boom
boom to spend on resolving conflicts
between the American Indians and the
migrating colonists. And to be clear,
this was not just theoretical. You see,
colonists had already started a conflict
with an alliance of American Indians
known as Pontiacs Rebellion. But even
so, the colonists were, as we say here
in the South, matter than a wet hen at
this proclamation. They believed that
they were owed this land on account of
their participation in the war that
helped Britain win it. And then the
third effect of this war, which I
already hinted at, was the problem of
Britain's war debt. Not only did it cost
a fortune to win the war, but the cost
of running the colonies had increased
five-fold, owing to the rapid population
growth there. Therefore, at this point,
Great Britain began implementing
policies aimed at tighter control over
the colonies so that they could earn
some muchneeded tax revenue. Okay. So,
at the end of the war, King George
appointed George Grenville as the
British prime minister, and he helped
develop a plan to reassert control in
the American colonies. First, Grenville
began enforcing existing laws that
colonists had routinely flouted on
account of salutary neglect. And chief
among these laws were the Navigation
Acts that restricted colonial trade to
Great Britain alone. Second, certain
wartime policies were kept in force
after the war was over. Especially nasty
was the Quartering Act, which required
colonial subjects to house and feed
members of the British military who were
there in response to the French and
Indian War as well as Pontiac's
rebellion. And then third and most
significant, Grenville persuaded
Parliament to enact a series of new
taxes on the colonies that would help
pay down Britain's war debt. Now, to
keep things simple, let's just focus on
one taxation law in particular, namely
the Stamp Act of 1765. This was just
attacks on paper items like newspapers
or diplomas or playing cards. And while
that may not seem like a huge deal, it
provoked colonial displeasure, something
awful. Now, there are several reasons
for that displeasure, but chief among
them was that the colonists resented
that they were being taxed without any
representation in parliament. In other
words, laws were being imposed on them
without their consent. And the whole
reason they felt thusly imposed upon was
because the colonists had grown used to
a significant degree of self-governance.
And so, they summarized their grumpies
with the now famous phrase, no taxation
without representation. Now to George
Grenville, this protest was altogether
puzzling. He argued that the colonists
did in fact have representation, namely
virtual representation in parliament. In
other words, members of parliament
represented the interest of all English
subjects, whether they were home or
living in a colony. And to be clear,
this was how all British subjects on the
mainland were represented in Parliament.
So, you know, the colonists were not
special here. But the colonists saw
things differently. You see, because
they had developed habits of self-ruule
over time, colonists believed that
representation must be local. And since
there were no members of the colonies in
Parliament, they believed that they
therefore had no representation. Now,
Grrenville ignored the colonist plea
with a mixture of broiling resentment
and classic British restraint and just
kept squeezing all the cash he could out
of the colonies. And that reality in
turn united the colonies in protest
against these grievous laws. Some gave
impassioned speeches or wrote pamphlets.
But the most significant mode of protest
was the formation of committees of
correspondence. By 1774, all but one of
the colonies had created a network of
these committees which organized and
spread information about colonial
grievances with speed. Additionally,
merchants, traders, and artisans created
groups like the Sons of Liberty and the
Daughters of Liberty, who fought for the
repeal of the Stamp Act. However, the
most formal and organized protest came
in the form of the Stamp Act Congress,
which convened in 1765. Here, delegates
from nine colonies formally petitioned
Parliament to repeal the Stamp Act
because taxation without representation
amounted to tyranny. However, there's
one very important point to remember
here. Neither the colonists nor the
delegates at the Stamp Act Congress were
agitating for independence from Britain
at this point. No, what they wanted was
to remain British subjects without
experiencing the infringement of their
British rights. Anyway, the work of
Congress combined with the widespread
boycotts of goods taxed by the Stamp Act
led Parliament to repeal the Stamp Act
in 1766. But about 5 minutes after that,
they also passed the Declaratory Act,
which essentially said that Parliament
is still in charge and could pass any
dang laws they wanted to. Look, I
repealed the Stamp Act because I wanted
to, not because you nagged me. Sure.
Sure. Now, this spat would go on for the
next few years. After all, Big Mama
still needed that colonial scratch for
her bank account. And so, Parliament
would pass new taxation laws, and
colonists would boycott the goods or
find other ways to frustrate Grenville's
plans. But starting in the 1770s, three
developments seriously cranked up the
heat on these tensions. First was the
Boston Massacre in 1770. Long story
short, occupying British soldiers opened
fire on a group of protesters in Boston
and end up killing five Bostononians.
Second was the Boston Tea Party in 1773.
Here, colonists protesting Britain's
increased efforts to control the
colonies dumped 50 tons of British tea
into the Boston Harbor. And then third,
Britain responded to this offense with
the Coercive Acts in 1774. Now, these
laws closed the Boston Harbor until the
tea was paid for and introduced a new
quartering act which mandated even more
soldiers must be accommodated in
colonial homes. You don't have to guess
how the colonists felt about that since
these laws in the colonies were policies
known as the Intolerable Acts. And such
a name made sense to the colonists
because this set of laws in their minds
represented the most significant grab
for power and control that they had yet
experienced from parliament. But even
with all this pressure on the colonies,
you still need to remember that for them
revolution was not yet the move. Even
now they wanted to remain British
subjects while enjoying the fullness of
their British rights. But all those
taxes and developments I just mentioned
combined with a piping hot stew of ideas
began to tip the scales into revolution
territory. So let's talk about that.
First, the proliferation of
enlightenment ideals contributed to a
revolutionary mindset. And there are two
of these ideas you'll need to know,
although there are certainly more you
could know. First is the idea of natural
rights, which by definition argues that
human beings are born with certain
rights, namely life, liberty, and
property. And those rights are given to
each individual by God and not a
monarch. Second, you have the social
contract. The idea here is that human
beings endowed with natural rights must
construct governments of their own will
and that the main purpose of that
government is to protect their natural
rights. Therefore, if the government
becomes tyrannical, thus violating the
contract, then the people have the right
to overthrow that government and replace
it with a new one. And then the second
set of ideas that contributed to a
revolutionary mindset were religious
ideas. Now recall that it was only a few
decades prior to this that the great
awakening had occurred. And this
movement emphasized individual religious
awakening and individual communion with
God. Like the emphasis was don't listen
to what the old crusty pointyatted
church hierarchy tells you to do. Listen
to what God tells you to do by means of
your own interpretation of the Bible.
And if you're paying attention, that
clearly signals a growing colonial
conviction to challenge traditional
authority structures. And one of the
chief effects of this widespread
movement was that the colonists started
believing that the liberty they enjoyed
was actually a gift from God. And so
when the dumb king and parliament came
in trampling on that liberty, it wasn't
just the colonists they were
challenging, but the dang almighty
himself who gave the colonies this
liberty. Therefore, as the colonist mind
were shaped by these ideas, they began
to believe that individual talent
trumped hereditary power. What I mean is
enlightenment ideas argued that
individuals had rights given by God and
that no arbitrary power structure could
infringe on those rights. The religious
ideas argued that individuals could
decide for themselves what God was
saying instead of relying on the power
structures found in the church. And I
think you begin to see how ideas like
this combined with all those
curtailments of liberty that I mentioned
before could start riing folks up for
revolution. But even still, the
revolution loaf had not yet risen in the
oven to its full doughy goodness. Like
even after the colonist convened the
first Continental Congress to centralize
resistance to British policy, still they
wanted to remain British subjects with
their full British rights. And even
after they convened the second
Continental Congress in response to
actual British aggression at Lexington
and conquered, many delegates maintained
that the best course of action was to
negotiate with Britain. And that was in
1775. But 1776 was the year of
revolution. So what in the fresh heck
change? Well, a very significant factor
was the publication of a deeply sassy
pamphlet by our boy Thomas Payne. It was
called Common Sense and it argued that
British tyranny had reached its peak and
the only way for the colonist to
preserve their liberty was to declare
independence. And this pamphlet sold
like crazy throughout the colonies and
convinced many folks that revolution was
inevitable. And one of the reasons it
spoke to so many people is that Payne
used the kind of arguments and evidence
that aligned with ideas already deeply
held by the colonists. For example,
Payne used enlightenment ideas like
natural rights and the social contract
and republicanism to demonstrate that
Britain was a tyrannical turd that
needed to be flush. He also used
biblical arguments and illusions, most
notably the development of monarchy in
the Old Testament and how God considered
it a sin. So by 1776, it was
independence time. So Thomas Jefferson
wrote the Declaration of Independence
and made the argument for separation
using, you guessed it, enlightenment
ideas like natural rights and the social
contract. And that, my dear pupils, is
how you start a revolution. Okay. Now,
before you get out your fireworks and
your star spangled tank tops, I need to
tell you why the Americans should not
have won this war. And then I'll tell
you why they ultimately did. And at that
point, you may excuse yourself and
high-five as many bald eagles as you
wish. But first, there were two main
factors that should have contributed to
a British victory in the American
Revolution. First was the presence in
the colonies of a significant loyalist
opposition. Now a loyalist was just
someone who did not support the
revolution and wanted to remain loyal to
Great Britain. And the best estimates
say that about 15 to 20% of the
colonists were loyalists. And to be
clear, only about half the population
supported the patriot cause for
independence. So that means the other
roughly 30% of the folks just didn't
want anything to do with either side and
wanted to keep as far from the troubles
as they could. But then the second
reason the British should have won is
the indisputable fact of their military
superiority. Like it wasn't even close.
Great Britain, if you'll recall, had
spent the majority of their time in the
last century building a global maritime
empire, the size of which would have
made Julius Caesar poop his pants or,
you know, his toga. I don't know. Did do
they have pants under the toasa?
>> Anyway, not the point. The point is, in
order to establish and maintain that
empire, Great Britain had a massive army
and the world's deadliest navy. And
those troops had plenty of practice
mowing down their enemies on account of
the nearly constant wars Great Britain
found themselves in. So, it's not
looking good for the colonists who just
declared independence. But, and I hope
this isn't a spoiler, the Americans did
win, and that was because of three very
important factors. First, we have the
leadership of George Washington. Now,
it's true that the soldiers that made up
the colonial militias and the
Continental Army were in general poorly
equipped, poorly trained, and often
deserted their post. And that meant in
the first six years of the war, the
Continental Army never won a single
victory in battle, and it appeared that
the overwhelming forces of the British
would prevail. But Washington was an
exceedingly capable leader, and he was
able to score some important victories.
First, his surprise attack at the Battle
of Trenton against Britain's hired
Hessen troops, while not a major
strategic victory, proved that the
Americans could in fact win. Second,
Washington enlisted a Prussian officer
named Friedrich Wilhelm von Stuben to
train the soldiers in the Continental
Army, and he was able to make a lot of
progress on their discipline. Okay. Now,
the second factor in the American
victory was their alliance with France.
You see, the Continental Congress had
sent Benjamin Franklin to France in 1776
to try to enlist their help against
Great Britain. But thus far, the French
would not ally with the colonist. And
that's mainly because the Americans
hadn't really proven that they could
actually win. And you know, like that's
important. But that changed with the
Battle of Saratoga in 1777, in which
patriot militias won a resounding
victory against British forces. And
after proving they could actually win,
the French went ahead and joined the war
against the British, sending aid and
troops and ships and all manner of
supplies that would ultimately lead to
an American victory. And finally, the
third factor that contributed to an
American victory was the colonist
ideological commitment and resilience.
And although this was kind of an
intangible factor, it was real potent
nonetheless. Like think about it. The
British motivation for fighting the war
was to maintain their economic and
political dominance in North America.
Lame. But for the patriots, the war was
an existential battle to secure liberty
and throw off tyranny. And I don't think
it's too hard to judge which was the
more powerful set of ideas. Now
ultimately those factors led to the
patriot victory and the American
Revolution in 1781. The final battle
being won at Yorktown. And in 1783, the
Treaty of Paris was signed, which both
ended the war and doubled the land
holdings of the freshly born United
States. And that's the end of act one.
So let's take a brief intermission.
Okay, that's enough. We need to move on
to act two. Okay, now before we get to
talking about all the flurry of
developments that created new
constitutions and governments and all of
that, let's stick for a moment with the
revolutionary ideals that helped sustain
the patriot victory. Yes, they
definitely helped energize the Americans
for military victory, but here's where I
tell you that those ideas had a
significant impact on American society
and across the world as well. First,
these revolutionary ideals led to calls
to address various social inequalities.
Two of which I'll tell you about now.
First of all, ideas about liberty and
equality of all people led to movements
to abolish slavery. mostly concentrated
in the north. You see, when black people
of all stripes heard Jefferson say that
all men are created equal, they assumed
that all men, including black men, were
equal, and therefore slavery had no
place in the New Republic. And some
states, when writing their new
constitutions, agreed with that logic.
For example, Vermont's Constitution
abolished slavery outright, and
Pennsylvania's made provision for the
gradual abolition of slavery. However,
to the elite planters in the south whose
entire way of life, not to mention their
wealth and status, depended on slavery,
they did not in fact believe that all
men included the black people they had
enslaved. So, here you can begin to see
differing regional attitudes taking
shape around the question of slavery and
whether the institution contradicted the
ideals on which the new nation was
founded. Okay. The second example here
is that revolutionary ideals led to
calls for greater political democracy.
You see, in the early years of the
republic, for the most part, the right
to vote was restricted to white property
owning men. And since those
revolutionary ideas about natural rights
and the social contract had become so
embedded in the American consciousness,
it seemed right to a lot of people that
the franchise would be expanded to more
and more people, particularly those
without land. Now, here's where I tell
you that even though these calls to
address inequality were the natural
consequence of ideas that made the
revolution, it would take a long time
before the inequalities were in fact
addressed. Okay. Second, revolutionary
ideas led to calls for women's equality.
Now, though they're not mentioned as
often as they should be, women played
significant roles in the victory over
Britain in the revolution. Therefore,
women certainly believe that the
equality for which the revolution was
fought ought to include them as well.
And contrary to what men like Thomas
Jefferson thought, women were actually
capable of more than just knitting socks
for their husbands or making his dang
sandwiches. Case in point, Abigail
Adams, who was a woman of fierce
intellect, wrote to her husband, John
Adams, while at the constitutional
convention. She encouraged the delegates
to remember the ladies as they were
constructing a new constitution on the
principles of liberty. But as you may
have guessed, the delegates did not in
fact remember the ladies and refused to
recognize their political equality in
the New Republic. However, I guess they
were in the mood to throw women a bone
because Benjamin Rush defined women's
role as participating in something
called the Republican motherhood.
Basically, the most important way a
woman could participate in a Republican
society was to thoroughly educate her
sons in the notions of liberty and
government. And while this notion
certainly kept women from active
political participation, it did expand
their access to education, which was a
welcome opportunity for many women. And
then third, revolutionary ideas
influenced other revolutions across the
Atlantic world based on those same
ideas. First was the French Revolution
in which the people overthrew the
monarch and established a republic.
Second was the Haitian Revolution in
which the majority enslaved black
population rose up against their French
overlords and established the first
black republic in history. And third,
the ideals of the American Revolution
inspired various Latin American
revolutions. So Creole military leaders
like Simone Bolivar appealed to colonial
subjects across racial lines with
enlightenment ideals, including appeals
to popular sovereignty and the right to
self-ruule among the various Spanish and
Portuguese colonies. And so through a
series of long and protracted wars, one
Latin American colony after another won
its independence and many of them formed
republican governments in its wake.
Okay, now it's time to talk about how
this brand spanking new republic is
going to govern itself. And so let's
start by talking about all the new state
governments and then we're going to
consider the formation of the federal
government. Now, right after declaring
independence, each state drafted a new
constitution. And there are two very
important commonalities that you need to
know. First, state constitutions created
governments in which most of the power
was concentrated in the legislature as
opposed to an executive or a governor.
And that's not hard to understand
because the legislature was the
representative body of the people. And
that's where the states wanted the power
after having so long been crushed under
the tyrannical centralized power thumb
of Great Britain. And then second, as I
mentioned earlier, most state
constitutions limited voting rights to
white male property owners. Okay. Now,
let's consider the formation of the
republic's new national or federal
government. So, in 1777, the Continental
Congress drafted the first Constitution
of the United States, namely the
Articles of Confederation. Now, the main
thing you need to remember about the
government created by the Articles is
this. It kept the federal government
exceedingly weak. So, in this first
political iteration of the United
States, the state governments held most
of the power while the federal
government was very weak. In fact, it
wasn't as much a federal government as
it was a fart in the shape of a
government. And while this limited
federal power satisfied Americans who
wanted to avoid centralized power at all
costs, the republic began facing
significant problems that began to show
the weaknesses of the articles to govern
effectively. There are five categories
of weaknesses that you're going to need
to know. First, the federal government
was too weak to solve problems related
to international trade. After the war,
Great Britain cut off trade between the
United States and the British West
Indies. And then Spain prohibited
American trade ships from accessing the
Mississippi River via Louisiana. And
then pirates off the Barbar Coast of
North Africa attacked US merchant ships.
And that made things real dire for the
new nation. But the federal government
with its glaring lack of centralized
power was helpless to remedy these
economic problems. Second, the federal
government struggled to address their
financial problem. For example, the
Congress had no constitutional authority
to collect tax revenue from the states
and so the federal government was broke
as a joke. But nobody was laughing at
that joke because a significant bill on
which the Congress was defaulting was
paying soldiers who had fought in the
Revolutionary War. Now, put that in your
pocket and we'll come back to it. The
third problem showing the weaknesses of
the federal government had to do with
interstate commerce. So because the
nation was more like a collection of
independent and powerful states, they
each competed with one another for
economic gain. So states put tariffs on
goods and hampered free trade in and
around the new republic. And the federal
government under the articles had no
authority to settle disputes over
interstate commerce. Fourth, foreign
relations were exposing the weaknesses
of the articles. You see, although Great
Britain had lost the war, they kept
forces occupying several forts along the
Western Frontier, and the federal
government had no way to stop this
egregious violation of the terms of
peace since they had no authority to
raise an army. And finally, the fifth
development that seriously exposed the
weakness of the federal government was
Sha's rebellion. Now, remember how I
said a second ago that Congress didn't
have the money to pay their war
veterans? Well, now that's about to be a
real problem. So, up in Massachusetts, a
group of angry farmers fed up with their
economic suffering attacked courouses in
the area and then stormed a federal
arsenal. They were led by a man named
Daniel Sheayes, and they intended to get
the money that they were owed from the
government. However, the Massachusetts
militia met the rebels and pretty
quickly suppressed the rebellion. But
this event had consequences all out of
proportion to the size of the battle.
You see, the chief effect of this event
was to show the intolerable weakness of
the Articles of Confederation. Because
there were unpaid veterans everywhere in
the States, fears were stoked that this
rebellion could be the start of many
more to follow. When they considered
that the federal government could do
nothing to stop it, they can either like
pay their veterans or raise an army to
defeat them, it became clear that a new
constitution was needed. And I'll tell
you about that in a moment. But first, I
should tell you that there's at least
one lasting and valuable thing that came
out of the federal government during
this time. It was the passage of the
Northwest Ordinance of 1787 which
regulated the vast and unsettled
territory that had come to the United
States as a result of the Treaty of
Paris. And not only did the ordinance
mandate that land be reserved for
schools, but it also banned slavery in
the territory. Additionally, it laid out
rules that dictated how territories in
the western region could become official
states. And even after the Articles of
Confederation was scrapped, this
ordinance remained and created the
conditions for several new states to
join the Union. Okay, so we've
established that the federal government
under the Articles was more like a fart
in the shape of a government. And now
it's time to bring in the fans to clear
that stank out. That's right, it's time
for a new constitution. So in 1787, 55
delegates met in Philadelphia at the
constitutional convention. Now the
stated goal was to revise the Articles
of Confederation. But the meeting
quickly shifted to the creation of a new
constitution altogether. The main
question that guided them was this. How
do we strengthen the federal government
without giving it so much power that it
becomes tyrannical? And after months of
debate and compromise, they ended up
answering that question by implementing
two principles. First, the Constitution
created a federal government
characterized by the separation of
powers. So, the federal government under
the articles only had one branch of
government, namely a legislature. So,
yeah, with only one branch, you better
not give it too much power. But the
constitution solved that problem by
creating three equal branches, each of
which would hold different aspects of
governing power, and each of which would
have power to check and balance the
other. So, the legislative branch would
be responsible for creating laws, and
that duty would be carried out by
Congress. The executive branch would be
responsible for enforcing the laws, and
that duty would be discharged by a
president. And then the judicial branch
will be responsible for interpreting the
constitutionality of laws and that duty
would fall to the Supreme Court. But the
second principle provided further
insurance against federal tyranny namely
federalism. So don't forget that the
constitution is only creating a federal
government. All those powerful state
governments are still around. So
federalism is a system of government in
which power is shared between the
federal and state governments. So some
powers are given to the federal
government alone like for example
declaring war. But other powers are
reserved exclusively for the states like
running elections. And then other powers
like taxation are shared by the federal
and state governments. So the point is
with power divided across three branches
of government and then further divided
between federal and state governments,
it seemed like a pretty good system for
avoiding the tyranny of centralized
power. Now this is how the constitution
eventually turned out. But getting to
that finish line required an enormous
amount of debate and compromise over
several key issues. Now one of the most
important debates had to do with how
representation would work in the new
government. And there were two
conflicting views. The Virginia plan
asserted that representation ought to be
reckoned by population and that favored
the interest of large states. But the
New Jersey plan argued that
representation should be reckoned
equally with one representative per
state and that favored the interests of
small states. Now ultimately what we got
was the great compromise which
established a biccameal legislature
which would consist of two houses. In
the House of Representatives,
representation would be population-based
and in the Senate representation would
be equal. Now speaking of compromises,
probably the debate that caused the most
heat at the convention concerned the
question of slavery. Weird, right?
Anyway, the first question had to do
with how to count enslaved people for
representation in the House of
Representatives. Northern delegates
thought they shouldn't be counted at
all, while southern delegates wanted
them counted as full members of the
population. What they got instead was
the three-fifths compromise, which said
that three-fifths of the enslaved
population of the state would count
towards representation. Now, the second
debate around slavery had to do with the
importation of enslaved people. But
again, after a bunch of red-faced,
sweaty debate, the compromise that made
it into the Constitution was this.
Congress could not touch the slave trade
for 20 years after the ratification of
the Constitution. And after that, the
international slave trade would be
abolished in 1808. Okay, so there were a
lot more debates and compromises that I
did not mention, but that's going to do
for our purposes. You just need to
realize that the constitution we got out
of that convention pleased precisely no
one entirely, and that meant it
represented a decent set of compromises.
But the story didn't end with the
writing of the Constitution. No, that
sweet bippy still had to be ratified by
nine out of 13 states in order for it to
take the place of the Articles of
Confederation. And wouldn't you know it,
just like there were sweaty debates
during the writing of the Constitution,
so were there equally sweaty debates
about whether the state should ratify.
And those debates were carried on by two
opposing factions. The Federalists, led
by Alexander Hamilton, argued for the
ratification of the Constitution. And
they articulated their arguments in a
series of essays known as the Federalist
Paper. And essentially, their line of
reasoning went like this. The federal
government needed to be strengthened if
the new republic was going to be able to
survive and thrive economically and
politically. And the constitution would
create such a government, but its power
would be limited by the separation of
powers and checks and balances. And then
on the other side, the anti-federalist
argued against ratification. They liked
having powerful states and a weak
central government. And they believed
that by strengthening the federal
government, that would only lead right
back to the problems they had with Great
Britain before the revolution.
Additionally, because the US was so
large and diverse, they argued that a
central government could not possibly
represent all interests equally. But
probably their biggest gripe was that
the constitution had no bill of rights
as many state constitutions had. Now,
ultimately the arguments of the
Federalist won the day and by June of
1788 enough states had ratified the
document and it became the law of the
land. However, the only way the
federalists were able to achieve this
was to pacify anti-federalist fears and
promise to include a bill of rights soon
after ratification, which they did.
Okay, now that the constitution had been
ratified, it's time to take this new
federal government for a spin and see
how she purs. Now, each of the three
branches of the federal government got
busy creating institutions and setting
precedents for future government
officials. And now that the government
had a little room to flex its freshly
juiced federal pectorals, let's have a
look at some of those important
developments. Now let's start with the
executive branch. The first president of
the United States was George Washington
who holds the distinction of being the
one and only president unanimously
elected by the electoral college. Now
the first President Washington set was
the formation of executive departments.
He created the department of state led
by Thomas Jefferson. Then there was the
department of war led by Henry Knox.
Also there was the department of the
treasury led by Alexander Hamilton. And
finally the department of justice was
led by Edmund Randall. Together, these
four men led their respective
departments and served as Washington's
cabinet of adviserss. And even though
the Constitution doesn't mandate this
division of labor in the executive
department, nor does it forbid such an
arrangement. And so, executive
departments in the president's cabinet
have been main stays in the executive
branch ever since. Okay. The second
important precedent Washington set was
to serve only two four-year terms in
office. Like, the Constitution of that
time did not limit the number of terms a
president can serve, but Washington
seemed to know by intuition that the
republic could best thrive if the
executive willingly surrendered power
after 8 years. That precedent lasted
until 1940 when Franklin Roosevelt was
elected for a third term and then a
fourth. But you know, it was a wild time
what with a great depression and World
War II and all. Regardless, after that,
the 22nd amendment formally restricted a
president's service to two terms.
Anyway, upon stepping down from office,
Washington gave a farewell address in
which he urged the new nation to avoid
two potential traps. First, he warned
against the divisive effects of
political parties and to avoid them at
all costs. Second, he warned against
committing to entangling foreign
alliances that would unnecessarily drag
the United States into wars with foreign
powers. But then if we shift over to the
legislative and judicial branches, we
also got the creation of an institution
that has lasted until this day. In 1789,
Congress passed the Judiciary Act, which
created a multi-level federal court
system. And that was important because
it seemed like when James Madison was
writing the Constitution and got to
Article 3, he was like, "Dang, my hand
hurts." But I'm sure they'll figure out
the courts. Uh, who's up for some pickle
ball? But anyway, the Judiciary Act
created a three- tiered court system.
You had 13 district courts, three courts
of appeals, and then the granddaddy of
all, the Supreme Court, which was
populated with six justices. And again,
the creation of that system has lasted
until the present, even if there have
been some minor additions and
subtractions. Now, the one thing that
the framers of the Constitution
emphatically did not account for in the
New Republic was the formation of
political parties. But like an unwanted
stench from a gym bag, political parties
formed of their own accord and made the
New Republic smell uh nasty. But why,
says you, did political parties form?
Well, says I. During the era of the New
Republic, the federal government faced a
multitude of events and developments.
And as it turned out, different factions
had different opinions on how to best
address them. And as those factions
curled themselves around their opinions
more and more, we see the emergence of
two political parties. The Federalist
and the Democratic Republican. And these
parties basically correspond to the
factions we saw pop up during the
ratification debates. The Federalist
Party led by Alexander Hamilton was the
direct descendant of the, you know,
Federalist. And then the Democratic
Republican Party led by Thomas Jefferson
was the direct descendant of the
anti-federalist. Now in general, the
federalist supported policies that
strengthen the federal government while
the Democratic Republicans supported
policies that strengthened state
governments. Okay, now let's talk about
the four issues the US faced that gave
birth to these two parties. The first
issue was a debate over economic policy.
And most important here is Hamilton's
proposal for the creation of a national
bank that would help establish US credit
and create the conditions for national
economic flourishing. Now, of course,
that would mean metric buttloads of
economic power and control for the
federal government. And the Democratic
Republicans hated this idea. And why?
Well, first, the Constitution has no
provision for the federal government to
create a bank. And second, Democratic
Republicans saw a national bank as a
power grab for the federal government
against the wealth and interest of
common farmers. Now, Hamilton ended up
winning this fight. And the National
Bank was established over the deafening
sound of the weeping and nashing of
Democratic Republican teeth. Okay. Now,
the second debate that gave rise to
political parties concerned the proper
balance between liberty and public
order. And by far the best example here
is the federal response to the whiskey
rebellion, which started in 1791. So at
Hamilton's urging, Congress imposed a
tax on whiskey in order to raise federal
revenue. Now this put serious economic
strain on western farmers and Democratic
Republicans viewed this tax as
federalist protection of industry at the
expense of those poor farmers.
Therefore, the farmers broke out in
rebellion much to the delight of Thomas
Jefferson who always seemed to prefer
revolution to the growth of federal
power. Now it might help to compare the
federal response to this rebellion to
the federal response to Sha's rebellion.
Now remember back then under the
articles there was no president. So when
the Massachusetts governor needed backup
and he called for federal assistance,
Beep beep beep hell. There was no one on
the other end of the line. But now
during the Whiskey Rebellion, it's the
age of the Constitution, baby. And when
Pennsylvania called for help, Washington
looked at Hamilton and was like, "Bro,
ho my mad dear." And responded with
force to suppress the rebellion. Now,
that response did two things. First, it
demonstrated that the new federal
government was far more capable than the
government under the articles to keep
order in the nation. But second, it
enraged the Democratic Republicans who
felt that the show of force against
legitimate rebellion amounted to
tyranny. Okay. Now the third debate that
gave rise to parties had to do with
foreign policy. And a good example here
is the eruption of the French Revolution
in 1789. The Democratic Republicans
believed that the US ought to come to
the aid of French revolutionaries since
they had come to the aid of the American
revolutionaries. I mean you know bro but
the federalists worried that by
involving themselves with the revolution
which had expanded by that point to
include wars with Great Britain and
Prussia and Austria that US trade
prospects would be harmed. Therefore
Washington issued a neutrality
proclamation which protected American
trade and kept the US from getting
involved. And that of course got
Democratic Republicans matter than a wet
hen and Thomas Jefferson went ahead and
resigned from Washington's cabinet in
protest. And then finally the fourth
event that helped draw the lines for
opposing parties was the proper
relationship between national and state
governments. And the big offender here
came in the form of the alien and
sedition acts passed during the term of
the second President John Adams. Now
basically these two laws made it
possible for the Adams administration to
use federal power to silence disscent
against federalist policy. And these
laws were passed in response to growing
fears about foreign influence during the
French Revolution and their conflict
with the British. That context and
justification aside, I don't think I
have to tell you why the Democratic
Republicans hated this. To put it
mildly, they downright hated this
development and thought federal power
had gone way out of bounds of its
constitutional limits. So, in response,
state legislators passed the Virginia
and Kentucky resolutions which stated
that the Alien and Sedition Acts were
unconstitutional and therefore
uninforceable. In fact, these
resolutions made it plain that any
federal law that enables the government
to operate beyond its constitutional
power should be considered null and void
by the states. And that, my dear people,
is going to come back on several
occasions in future units. So get
excited. Okay. Now the final act of this
period drama is going to tie up some
loose ends and we're going to start with
the emergence of a national identity and
how that contrasted with regional
identities. So in terms of a national
identity, much of how Americans began to
think of themselves was defined by the
concept of liberty. In their own
imaginations, to be an American was to
be free. And you can see evidence of
this as states wrote their constitutions
and abolished titles of aristocracy
which have been used to oppress them
during the colonial age. Also, state
constitutions enacted various degrees of
religious toleration. Americans they
argued should be free to worship as they
pleased without the forced submission to
a state church. But also evidence of a
burgeoning national identity started
showing up in art and literature and
architecture. As for art, let me
introduce you to Charles Wilson Peele
who was known for painting revolutionary
war leaders like Washington and Franklin
and Jefferson as Republican heroes. And
you can see that his subjects were
romanticized and the point was to
convince Americans who their heroes were
and that of course contributed to the
formation of a national identity. And as
for literature, a good example is Hector
St. John de Krevker. Now he's considered
one of the first American novelists and
one of his main contributions to the
development of a national identity was
his description of the American as a new
man that blended European roots with
frontier opportunity. As for
architecture, prominent US buildings
like the capital were built in the
federal style of architecture, which was
a rejection of the Georgian style that
represented British sensibilities. But
even with all that going on, regional
identities remained strong and varied
significantly from one another. Maybe
the best example here is the way
different regions understood the notion
of liberty. Now, as I mentioned before,
some states in the north moved toward
the emancipation of enslaved blacks,
while southern states that relied
heavily on enslaved labor allowed the
institution to remain entrenched in
their society. But even if enslaved
blacks were not considered in
Southerners's understanding of liberty,
many found their own way to take up the
voice of free people. For example, Gowen
Pamphlet was formerly enslaved but
gained his freedom and afterward he
became a minister of America's earliest
black Baptist congregation. And in that
way, he was able to demonstrate how
marginalized voices could still claim
their portion of the American identity
even when the rest of society was not
ready to deliver on its promises. And
now, ladies and gentlemen, the final
scene is upon us. Let us now consider
migration and all the conflict that it
caused. So remember what I said before,
namely that one of the results of the
Treaty of Paris, which ended the
revolution, was that the territory of
the US effectively doubled. And then
further remember that such a windfall of
land was a dream come true to the metric
buttloads of Americans who were hungry
to migrate west. And hey, I'm a big fan
of following your dreams. But on this
occasion, that dream was filled with
hostile Spanish and British garrisons
and American Indian groups. And so, to
put it mildly, the flood of migrants
into the Western Territory caused some
conflict. You see, even though the
British and Spanish maintained a
presence in the Western Territory,
Americans were keen to migrate and to
settle and therefore convince American
Indians who lived there that the land
belonged to them and not some European
power. And so, as they migrated and
settled, often without legal ownership
of the land, American Indians were
displaced and took up residence in
smaller and smaller tracks of land. and
that resulted in new American Indian
alliances that formed to resist the
migration of white settlers. Now to
further add to this growing conflict,
Great Britain had not honored the
agreement in the Treaty of Paris to
evacuate their post on the western
border and instead armed American
Indians and encouraged them to attack
American settlements in the Ohio River
Valley. And then Spain went ahead and
did the same in the south, arming Creeks
and Cherokees who used those weapons to
resist American westward migration. Now,
not surprisingly, this was a great
annoyance both to the migrants and to
the US government. So, in order to
address these increasing conflicts, in
1794, George Washington dispatched about
2,000 American soldiers into the Ohio
country. There, they fought against an
alliance of American Indians at the
Battle of Fallen Timbers. Now, US troops
won handily, and the conflict was ended
with the signing of the Treaty of
Greenville, which effectively opened the
Ohio territory for US settlement without
resistance. In that same year, Jay's
treaty was signed in which Great Britain
agreed to withdraw its forces from the
western borderlands in the US. And then
two years later, the US ratified the
Pinkney Treaty with Spain, which
formally recognized the borders between
the US and Spanish territory while also
opening the port of New Orleans and the
Mississippi River to US merchants. And
this effectively ended the Spanish
opposition to US westward expansion in
the south and reduced the conflict
between the two states. With all those
developments in the bag, westward
migration spiked and although their
movement didn't go entirely unopposed,
it was certainly easier than it was
before these events. But then the last
consequence I want to mention about
migration is the spread of slavery and
the conflicts that such a spread caused.
So, southern planters were especially
desirous to migrate westward in search
of new land to plant. And that's because
high demand crops like tobacco and
cotton depleted the soil of its
nutrients. And therefore, in order to
keep pace, especially with European
demand, they began to migrate westward
in large numbers. And as they moved, not
surprisingly, they brought slavery with
them. And that created a whole new
conflict in the new nation. Now,
southerners, of course, wanted no
hindrance to the westward expansion of
slavery. And that's not hard to
understand because most of their economy
deeply depended on it. But in the
northern states, alarm bells started
ringing as slavery expanded. Now, some
were abolitionists who objected to
slavery on moral grounds, and often they
were religious people like the Quakers
or the Menanites. And then others had
strictly economic motives for objecting
to slavery. Like in their minds, free
labor was a threat to paid labor, which
was the dominant labor system in the
North. Now, this debate is certainly not
going to be settled in this time period,
but don't worry, we're going to fight an
entire stinking civil war over it. So,
stay tuned. And that is unit 3. So, you
can click here to get my Heimler review
guide, which is everything you need to
get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May. Or you can click here
to check out my other topic videos for
unit 3. I appreciate you coming around
and I'll catch you on the flipflop.